Michael Aikey New York Imprints Research Files
Michael Aikey New York Imprints Research Files
circa 1802-1892 and 1960-1990
Aikey, Michael.
2 linear ft.
Research files relating to early (17th, 18th and 19th century) New York State printers and publishers, including ephemera and printed material from the era. Indexes, notes, clippings, etc.
2705298
Biographical History
Michael Aikey is the Director of the New York State Military History Museum and Veterans Research Center in Watervliet, New York. He is knowledgeable in both New York State military history and New York State printing history.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Michael Aikey New York Imprints Research Files consists of material accumulated by Mr. Aikey over the course of his research on early New York State publishers, printers and printing history in the 17th, 18th, and 19th centuries. The collection consists of binders, indexes, subject files, and miscellaneous items; much of it is photocopied material or handwritten notes.
All items retain the titles or headings given by Aikey, where available. Titles supplied during processing for unlabeled items are enclosed in square brackets [ ].
Binders contain material originally in four binders of varying sizes and formats. Material has been removed from the binders but remains in original order. Much of this is photocopies of title pages of early printed books, printouts of catalog entries, and similar reference material.
Indexes and bibliographies consists of an index created by Aikey of names appearing in History of the Press in Western New-York from the Beginning to the Middle of the Nineteenth Century, by Frederick Follett (the full text of this book is available via Google Books), and a set of index cards which appear to be a working bibliography of early New York imprints, with titles and printers/publishers.
Subject files relate primarily to printers in Troy, New York, though some concerns New York generally. Much of this material is photocopied articles from newspapers, magazines, or books.
Miscellaneous items consist of an untitled folder of photocopies and a small photograph album with a printout from a website regarding the Matthews and Lee family genealogies; the first picture in the album is labeled "Samuel C. Dutton." There is also a box of twenty or so assorted manuscripts, business ephemera, and partially printed forms (e.g. indentures) pertaining to printing and publishing in upstate New York.
Arrangement of the Collection
All series are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has numerous manuscript collections relating to printing and publishing. Please refer to for a complete listing. In addition, our Rare Books Collection contains numerous examples of early New York imprints, many from the collections of Monsignor Edward J. Byrne, Karl S. Kabelac, and Henry Bannister. Please search for these related materials.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Publishing, printing and book arts; Book industries and trade -- New York (State) -- History.; Booksellers and bookselling -- New York (State) -- History.; Early printed books.; Printing -- New York (State) -- History.; New York (State) -- Imprints.; Bibliographies.; Correspondence.; Indentures.; Indexes (reference sources); Photograph albums.; Research notes.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired in conjunction with purchase of Aikey's collection of early New York printed material, 2009.
Inventory
- Binders
  - First printing in NYS Communities, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Troy and Lansingburgh Imprints (Box 1)
  - Vol. 25, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - [Untitled] (Box 1)
- Indexes and bibliographies
  - Index to printers and publishers names in Follett's History of the Press in Western NY. Also editors (Box 2)
  - [Index card file, appears to be working bibliography of early NY imprints with title, publisher, etc] (Box 2)
- Subject files
  - McMurtrie "Geneva Imprints (1800-1850)" (Box 3)
  - McMurtrie, Schenectady Imprints (Box 3)
  - Printing history (Box 3)
  - Printing history, Troy, NY (Box 3)
  - Troy bookselling / booksellers (Box 3)
  - Troy imprints
    - Troy imprints (Box 3)
    - Bibliography (Box 3)
    - Bibliographic printouts holdings (Box 3)
    - Exhibit at RCHS, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Milton Thomas talks (Box 3)
    - Newspapers (Box 3)
  - Troy printers
    - Troy printers (Box 3)
    - Printers biographies (Box 3)
    - William Parker Bliss (Troy Post) (Box 3)
    - Robert Moffitt (Northern Budget) (Box 3)
    - Luther Pratt (Box 3)
    - Obadiah Penniman (Box 3)
    - William Wands (American Spy), Sylvester Tiffany (Box 3)
    - Goodenow Stockwell Wright (Troy Gazette) (Rensselaer Bookstore), Thomas Collier, John C. Wright (Box 3)
  - Wall. List of NY Almanacs, 1694-1850 (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  - [untitled folder] (Box 3)
  - [Dutton C. Seymour photograph album], circa 1862 (Box 3)
  - Ontario Repository (Canandaigua, NY) MAY 3, 1803 thru APR 16, 1805, 1 reel microfilm (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1802-1895; assorted manuscripts, business ephemera, and partially printed forms (e.g. indentures) pertaining to printing and publishing in upstate New York (Oversize 1)